Guide to the Bruce Maguire / Student YMCA Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Bruce Maguire / Student YMCA Papers
1921-1985
RG 78
Yale University Divinity School Library
16
(40 boxes)
The papers document the work of the Student Young Men's Christian Association primarily during the period when Bruce Maguire served as the Executive Secretary, 1955-1970. They provide insight into the activities and thought of American college students during this turbulent era and provide detailed information about the operations and policy of the Student YMCA as it sought to define its role in a changing society. Bruce Maguire was involved in student work for the YMCA from 1942 to 1971. From 1955-1970 he was Executive Secretary in the Student Department and National Student Council of YMCAs.
Maguire, Bruce
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Bruce Maguire
Biographical / Historical
1911May 26 Bruce Brownlie Maguire born in Youngstown, Ohio
1932 B.A., Muskingum College, New Concord, Ohio
1936 B.Th., Pittsburgh-Xenia Theological Seminary, Pittsburgh, PA
1936 M.A., University of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh, PA
1936 Aug 25 Married to Ruth L. Maguire. Children: G. Andrew, 1939 and Marjorie Lynn, 1941.
1936-1938 Presbyterian Board of Christian Education and Board of National Missions; Presbyterian University Pastor, Murray State Teachers College, Murray, Kentucky
1938-1939 Graduate study in personnel and higher education, Ohio State University, Columbus, Ohio
1939-1942 Mount Auburn Presbyterian Church, Cincinnati, Ohio; ministry in university community
1940-1942 Staff correspondent for The Christian Century
1942-1955 Pacific Southwest Area Council of YMCAs Area Student Secretary
1955-1968 National Board of Young Men's Christian Associations: Executive, Student Department and Executive, National Student Council of YMCAs; During this period, BBM was instrumental in the initial creation of:YMCA-YWCA Students-in-Industry Project on West Coas, Student YMCA-YWCA West Coast Leadership School, Religion and Labor Council of Los Angeles, USA-USSR Student Exchange (YMCA participation), Junior World Service Worker Project of the YMCA, Buildings for Brotherhood Work Camps
1957 Author of The University, the Church, and the YMCA
1969 Director of Planning, Constituent Services Division, National Board of YMCAs Author of The Revolution of the Young (Chapter 1 of YMCA Yearbook, pre-printed as pamphlet)
1970 Executive Assistant to Executive Director, National Board of YMCAs Staff related to Committee on Christian Concerns and Ecumenical Relations
1971 Staff Director of a study of the future direction of the YMCA in Metropolitan Washington
1972-1974 Fund Raising Campaign Consultant employed by Crook, Robinson and Clough, Montclair, NJ
1974-1982 Political campaign volunteer for son, Andrew Maguire
1970-1987 Active volunteer, Community Church of Glen Rock, New Jersey
Scope and Contents
These records document the work of the Student Young Men's Christian Association primarily during the period when Bruce Maguire served as the Executive Secretary, 1955-1970. They provide insight into the activities and thought of American college students during this turbulent era and provide detailed information about the operations and policy of the Student YMCA as it sought to define its role in a changing society.
These papers complement many of the other YMCA-related archival collections at Yale Divinity School Library, including the Archives of the YMCA - Student Division, the World Student Christian Federation, the Student Volunteer Movement, the Student Christian Movement in New England and the New England Commission for United Ministries in Higher Education, as well as the papers of various individuals who played important roles in the development of the YMCA. Taken as a whole, these records provide extensive documentation of religious work among college and university students throughout the twentieth century.
The material within each series of Record Group 78 is grouped according to specific subdivisions. For example, the National Administrative Bodies of Series I are categorized in a hierarchical fashion according to the formal name of each specific administrative body. Items in Series III relating to regional and local YMCAs are grouped into two categories, Area/State/Regional YMCAs and College/University YMCAs, and are arranged by proper place names within each group. Series V, Programs, Projects, further exemplifies this type of arrangement. The logic of this method of subdivision for each series is explained in detail in the series descriptions.
Material within each series subgroup is arranged according to the nature of individual items. The resulting distribution of the papers is summarized as follows:
Communications
Reports and Policy Records
Rosters
Notes
Books
Serials
Pamphlets
Clippings and Articles
Audiovisual Materials
Communications consist of correspondence, memos, enclosures and papers included for the addressee's information. Reports and policy records are papers pertaining to the administrative operation of the Student YMCA divisions. Financial statements are included in this category. Rosters consist of lists of students, staff, or branch YMCAs serving on specific YMCA committees or participating in particular YMCA events. Notes serve as Bruce Maguire's personally handwritten commentary on the contents of the file and also include notes taken at meetings and drafts of letters. Printed material, published by YMCA divisions and related organizations, consists of books, serials, pamphlets, clippings and articles. A publicity tape and several photographs relating to the Asilomar conference are found in Series IV, necessitating the assignment of the additional category of Audiovisual Materials.
The material in Series I provides much evidence of the interrelations between the national administrative bodies. Other series further detail their cooperation as they jointly sponsored, organized or participated in various YMCA committees, seminars, conferences, programs, and college activities, or merely supported each other's efforts. In contrast, Series I also reveals the ongoing quest for the administrative independence of the bodies. This is evident in significant communications and policy records which state the scope of authority of the bodies, as well as in less substantial matters such as designating the privilege of using letterhead stationery to certain groups and individuals.
Commissions, Committees and Personnel, Series II, detail the policies set up by designated subgroups of the YMCA administrative bodies. This series offers valuable insight into their procedures for realizing the goals of YMCA projects. Of particular interest are job descriptions in the personnel files which itemize the various duties of YMCA positions.
Series III, IV and V offer interesting information on the variety of activities sponsored by the YMCA all over the world, such as YMCA internships, Career Try-Out program, Urban Field Study, and the Young Voters' Task Force. Pamphlets and brochures highlight these activities with photographs and slogans.
Series VI was created for subjects of special interest which relate to the YMCA in general. Substantial material on the Lay Movement, National Student Caucus, National Student Christian Federation in the process of becoming the University Student Christian Movement, Religion in Higher Education, the student strikes against racism and Vietnam, and YMCA/YWCA relations is available in this series. A poster and newspaper article regarding the Japanese during World War II are of particular interest. Material collected from related organizations shows their relationship and cooperation with the YMCA.
While every series contains material by, about and collected by Bruce Maguire, his role as Executive Secretary of the YMCA is probably best revealed in Series VIII. This is a compilation of his personal correspondence, biographical information and notebooks.
Arrangement
I. National Administrative Bodies
II. Commissions, Committees, Personnel
III. Regional and Local YMCAs
IV. Seminars, Conferences
V. Programs, Projects
VI. Special Subjects
VII. Collected Printed Materia
VIII. Personal File of Bruce Maguire
College students -- Religious life; Universities and colleges -- Religion; Young Men's Christian Associations; Clergy; Maguire, Bruce; YMCA of the USA
- National Administrative Bodies, Series I
  Scope and Contents
  The national administrative bodies of the Young Men's Christian Association are arranged in hierarchical fashion.
  The administrative bodies represented in this series include:
  National Council
  National Board
  National Board Student Department
  National Student Council
  National Student Council - Headquarters and Field Staff
  National Student Committee
  National Student Committee - Executive Committee
  National Student Assembly
  Student Secretaries Association
  Materials are subdivided according to their nature, and are arranged chronologically within each subgroup.
  - National Council of YMCAs
    - Communications, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Reports/Policy Records, 1949-1970 (Box 1, Folder 2-5)
    - Printed Materials: Books, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Printed Materials Pamphlets, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - National Board of YMCAs
    - Reports/Policy Records, 1957-1958, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Printed Materials: Books (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - National Board - Student Department
    - Communications, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
    - Reports/Policy Records, 1949-1968 Jul (Box 1, Folder 12-14)
    - Reports/Policy Records, 1968-1969, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 15-16)
    - Notes, 1967-1968, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 17-19)
  - National Student Council of YMCAs
    - Communications, 1942-1964 Jul (Box 2, Folder 20-28)
    - Communications, 1964 Jul-1970 (Box 3, Folder 29-38)
    - Communications re. publications, 1956-1967 (Box 3, Folder 39-40)
    - Reports/Policy Records, 1954-1955 (Box 3, Folder 41-42)
    - Reports/Policy Records, 1955-1958 (Box 4, Folder 43-49)
    - Reports/Policy Records, including Administrative Committee and College Camp, 1958-1960 (Box 5, Folder 50-57)
  - National Student Council of YMCAs
    - Reports/Policy Records, including Administrative Committee and College Camp, 1960-1962 (Box 6, Folder 58-65)
    - Reports/Policy Records, 1962-1964 (Box 7, Folder 66-74)
    - Reports/Policy Records, 1964-1965 (Box 8, Folder 75-83)
    - Reports/Policy Records, 1965-1966 (Box 9, Folder 84-87)
    - Reports/Policy Records, 1967-1970, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 88-96)
    - Financial Statements, 1946-1968, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 97)
    - Rosters, 1956-1969, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 98)
    - Notes, 1956-1966 (Box 10, Folder 99)
    - Notes, 1967-1969, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 100)
    - Printed Material: Books: A-F (Box 11, Folder 101)
    - Printed Material: Books: I-Y (Box 11, Folder 102)
    - Printed Material: Serials (Miscellaneous), 1965-1967 (Box 11, Folder 103)
    - Printed Material: Pamphlets, 1950-1969, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 104-105)
    - Printed Material: Clippings and Articles, 1957-1968 (Box 11, Folder 106)
  - National Student Council of YMCAs Headquarters and Field Staff
    - Communications, 1955-1967, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 107-108)
    - Reports/Policy Records, 1956-1963 Jan (Box 11, Folder 109-112)
    - Reports/Policy Records, 1963-1966, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 113-117)
    - Notes, 1958-1966, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 118-119)
  - National Student Committee
    - Communications, 1959-1968 (Box 12, Folder 120)
    - Reports/Policy Records, 1956-1958 May (Box 12, Folder 121-126)
    - Reports/Policy Records, 1958 Nov-1962 (Box 13, Folder 127-137)
    - Reports/Policy Records, 1962 Nov-1966 (Box 14, Folder 138-147)
    - Reports/Policy Records, 1966 Nov-1967 (Box 15, Folder 148-150)
  - National Student Committee, Executive Committee
    - Reports/Policy Records, 1959-1967 (Box 15, Folder 151-158)
    - Notes, 1962-1966, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 159-160)
  - National Student Assembly of YMCAs
    - Communications, 1962-1967, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 161-162)
    - Reports/ Policy Records, 1951-1957 (Box 16, Folder 163-164)
    - Reports/Policy Records, 1958-1963 Jan 2 (Box 17, Folder 165-168)
    - Reports/Policy Records, 1963-1967 (Box 18, Folder 169-171)
    - Rosters, 1962-1967 (Box 18, Folder 172-173)
    - Printed Materials: Serials, 1941-1967 (Box 18, Folder 174-177)
    - Printed Materials: Pamphlets, 1937-1967, n.d. (Box 18, Folder 178-181)
    - Printed Materials: Clippings and articles, 1959-1963 (Box 18, Folder 182)
    - Photographs, 1966 (Box 18, Folder 183)
  - Student Secretaries Association
    - Communications, 1963-1969 (Box 18, Folder 184)
- Commissions, Committees, Personnel, Series II
  Material pertaining to commissions and committees formed within the YMCA administrative bodies are arranged alphabetically by their proper names. A chronological arrangement follows within specific groups.
  Job commissions and descriptions, detailing the duties and qualifications necessary for YMCA positions, follow a similar arrangement.
  - Area/State/Regional Consultations, 1965, n.d. (Box 19, Folder 185)
  - Committee on Campus Work, 1964 (Box 19, Folder 186)
  - Committee on College and University Work, 1964-1968 (Box 19, Folder 187)
  - Committee on Friendly Relations Among Foreign Students, 1953, n.d. (Box 19, Folder 188)
  - Committee on Member Associations, 1964, 1965 (Box 19, Folder 189)
  - Coordinating Committee on Student YMCA Work in New England, 1962 (Box 19, Folder 190)
  - Committee on Student YMCA and YWCA Relationships, 1964, 1965 (Box 19, Folder 191)
  - The Commission on the Need and Relevance of the National Student Council of YMCAs, 1968 (Box 19, Folder 192)
  - Consultation on Student Work, 1967 (Box 19, Folder 193)
  - Job Commissions, 1949-1963, n.d (Box 19, Folder 194)
  - Job Descriptions, 1946-1967 (Box 20, Folder 195-197)
  - Operating Goals, Constitutions, 1951-1968, n.d. (Box 20, Folder 198)
  - Personnel Appraisals: E-S (Box 20, Folder 199)
  - General: Communications, 1959-1967 (Box 20, Folder 200)
  - General: Reports/Policy Records, 1944, 1960, 1963 (Box 20, Folder 201)
  - General: Rosters, 1960-1961 (Box 20, Folder 202)
- Regional and Local YMCAs, Series III
  This series contains material relating to regional and local YMCAs around the United States. The papers have been divided into two subgroups, Area/State/Regional and College and University YMCAs. Items in the first subgroup are organized alphabetically by geographical region, and papers from college and university YMCAs are grouped similarly according to the name of the institution.
  - Area/State/Regional
    - General, 1950-1966, n.d. (Box 21, Folder 203)
    - Central Atlantic Area, 1967, n.d. (Box 21, Folder 204)
    - New England Area (Box 21, Folder 205)
    - North Central Area, 1964 (Box 21, Folder 206)
    - Pacific Northwest Area, 1961-1965, n.d. (Box 21, Folder 207)
    - Pacific Southwest Area: Communications, 1955 (Box 21, Folder 208)
    - Pacific Southwest Area: Reports/Policy Records, 1940-1955 (Box 21, Folder 209-214)
    - Pacific Southwest Area: Reports/Policy Records, 1956-1966 (Box 22, Folder 215)
    - Pacific Southwest Area: Rosters, 1921-1955 (Box 22, Folder 216)
    - Pacific Southwest Area: Notes, 1951-1952, n.d. (Box 22, Folder 217)
    - Pacific Southwest Area: Printed Material, 1949-1955, n.d. (Box 22, Folder 218-219)
    - Southern Area, 1964-1967 (Box 22, Folder 220)
    - Southwest Area: Communications, 1964-1965 (Box 22, Folder 221)
    - Southwest Area: Reports/Policy Records, 1961-1969, n.d. (Box 22, Folder 222)
    - Southwest Area: Notes, 1961-1969, n.d. (Box 22, Folder 223)
    - West Central Area: Communications, 1964-1966 (Box 22, Folder 224)
    - West Central Area: Printed Material, 1966 (Box 22, Folder 225)
    - State YMCAs: A-W (Box 22, Folder 226-227)
  - College and University YMCAs
    - General, n.d. (Box 22, Folder 228)
    - B - Calif (Box 22, Folder 229)
    - Calif (Box 23, Folder 230)
    - Cal T (Box 23, Folder 231)
    - City - Fres (Box 23, Folder 232)
    - G - I (Box 23, Folder 233)
    - O - P (Box 23, Folder 234)
    - S (Box 23, Folder 235)
    - T-W (Box 23, Folder 236)
- Seminars, Conferences, Series IV
  The papers in this series follow an alphabetical arrangement by the specific names of the seminars and conferences. Communications, reports/policy records, rosters, notes and printed materials pertaining to these meetings are arranged in chronological order. A publicity tape and several photographs of the annual Asilomar conference are included in this series.
  - Asilomar: Reports/Policy Records, 1947-1965, n.d. (Box 24, Folder 237-239)
  - Asilomar: Rosters, 1922-1955 (Box 24, Folder 240)
  - Asilomar: Notes, 1944-1954 (Box 24, Folder 241)
  - Asilomar: Serials: Remembrancer, 1944-1947 (Box 24, Folder 242-244)
  - Asilomar: Pamphlets, 1946-1963, n.d. (Box 24, Folder 245)
  - Asilomar: Show Programs, 1951, 1953, n.d. (Box 24, Folder 246)
  - Asilomar: Audio-Visual Materials: Publicity Tape, n.d. (Box 24, Folder 247)
  - Asilomar: Photographs: Unidentified Groups, 1951-1954, n.d. (Box 24, Folder 248)
  - Illinois Institute of Technology: Communications, 1966 (Box 25, Folder 249)
  - Illinois Institute of Technology: Notes, 1966, n.d. (Box 25, Folder 250)
  - Illinois Institute of Technology: Printed Material, n.d. (Box 25, Folder 251)
  - International Seminars/Conferences: A - F (Box 25, Folder 252)
  - Staff Seminar: Communications, 1965 (Box 25, Folder 253)
  - Staff Seminar: Reports/Policy Records, 1956-1963 (Box 25, Folder 254-256)
  - Staff Seminar: Rosters, 1956-1965 (Box 25, Folder 257-259)
  - Staff Seminar: Notes, 1956, 1963 (Box 25, Folder 260-261)
  - Staff Seminar: Printed Material, 1956, 1963 (Box 25, Folder 262-263)
  - Staff Seminar: Pre- and Post- Seminar Orientation Conferences, 1953-1960 (Box 25, Folder 264)
  - Staff Seminar: Task Groups, 1956 (Box 25, Folder 265)
  - Staff Seminar: Task Groups, 1960, n.d. (Box 26, Folder 266)
  - Staff Seminar: Notebook, 1959 (Box 26, Folder 267)
  - Staff Seminar: Notebook, 1959 (Box 26, Folder 267)
  - Washington Citizenship Seminar, 1962-1967 (Box 26, Folder 269)
  - Young Adult Assembly, 1964 (Box 26, Folder 270)
  - Miscellaneous Seminars/Conferences: Communications, 1956 (Box 26, Folder 271)
  - Miscellaneous Seminars/Conferences: Reports/Policy Records, 1951-1958 (Box 26, Folder 272)
  - Miscellaneous Seminars/Conferences: Printed Material, 1944-1969, n.d. (Box 26, Folder 273)
- Programs, Projects, Series V
  The material in this series is divided into two subgroups, Domestic Programs and International Programs. Following several folders of general material, the papers are organized alphabetically by program name. International programs are represented primarily by printed brochures and pamphlets and are arranged by country.
  - Domestic Programs
    - Communications, 1958-1969, n.d. (Box 27, Folder 274)
    - Reports, Proposals, Summaries, 1946-1968 (Box 27, Folder 275)
    - Planning: Communications, 1963-1965 (Box 27, Folder 276)
    - Planning: Reports/Policy Records, 1949-1965, n.d. (Box 27, Folder 277-278)
    - Planning: Financial, 1963-1964 (Box 27, Folder 279)
    - Planning: Rosters, 1959-1963 (Box 27, Folder 280)
    - Planning: Notes, 1956-1964, n.d. (Box 27, Folder 281-282)
    - Printed Material, 1962-1968, n.d. (Box 27, Folder 283)
    - Case Study Series:City YMCAs in Student Work: General, 1963-1964, n.d. (Box 27, Folder 284)
    - Case Study Series:City YMCAs in Student Work: Bloomington, 1967 (Box 27, Folder 285)
    - Case Study Series:City YMCAs in Student Work: Boston, 1966-1967 (Box 27, Folder 286)
    - Case Study Series:City YMCAs in Student Work: Dallas, 1963 (Box 27, Folder 287)
    - Case Study Series:City YMCAs in Student Work: Newark, 1963 (Box 27, Folder 288)
    - Community/Junior College Students, 1967-1968, n.d. (Box 27, Folder 289)
    - Forward (Advance) Program, 1950-1963, n.d. (Box 27, Folder 290-292)
    - Interns, 1965-1969, n.d. (Box 28, Folder 293-296)
    - Leadership Training Schools, 1951-1966, n.d. (Box 28, Folder 297)
    - Near Peer, 1967-1968, n.d. (Box 28, Folder 298-299)
    - Spectrum: General, 1966-1968 (Box 28, Folder 300-302)
    - Spectrum: Correspondence with Ford Foundation, 1966-1967 (Box 28, Folder 303)
    - Spectrum: Urban Field Study Aides, 1966 (Box 28, Folder 309)
    - Staff Study Program, 1945-1957, n.d. (Box 29, Folder 310-311)
    - Summer Programs, 1953-1970 (Box 29, Folder 312-314)
    - Tutoring, 1964-1968, n.d. (Box 29, Folder 315)
    - Urban Confrontation, 1971, n.d. (Box 29, Folder 316)
    - Work-Study Program, 1966 (Box 29, Folder 317)
    - Young Voters Project Catalyst, 1969, n.d. (Box 29, Folder 318)
    - Young Voters Project Catalyst: Independent Precinct Organization (Box 29, Folder 319)
    - Young Voters Task Force: Communications, 1967-1969, n.d. (Box 29, Folder 320-323)
    - Young Voters Task Force: Notes, 1969, n.d. (Box 29, Folder 324)
    - Young Voters Task Force: Clippings and Articles, 1968-1969, n.d. (Box 29, Folder 325)
    - Related Organizations and Publications: C - L (Box 30, Folder 326)
    - Related Organizations and Publications: U - Y (Box 30, Folder 327)
    - University/Area Programs: A - L (Box 30, Folder 328)
    - University/Area Programs: M - P (Box 30, Folder 329)
    - University/Area Programs: R - W (Box 30, Folder 330)
    - Miscellaneous YMCA Programs, 1970 (Box 30, Folder 331)
    - Programs Sponsored by Other Organizations: C - N (Box 30, Folder 332)
    - Programs Sponsored by Other Organizations: U - W (Box 30, Folder 333)
    - Programs Sponsored by American Friends Service Committee: I - W (Box 30, Folder 334)
    - Programs Sponsored by American Friends Service Committee: Printed Materials, 1951, n.d. (Box 30, Folder 335)
  - International Programs
    - Communications (incl. re. interns), 1957-1966 (Box 30, Folder 336-340)
    - Communications (incl. re. interns), 1967-1970, n.d. (Box 31, Folder 341-343)
    - Reports/Policy Records, 1956-1966 (Box 31, Folder 344-350)
    - Rosters, 1961-1970 (Box 31, Folder 351)
    - Notes, 1962-1968, n.d. (Box 31, Folder 352)
    - Printed Material: General, 1960-1970, n.d. (Box 32, Folder 353)
    - Printed Material: Africa, Asia (Box 32, Folder 354)
    - Printed Material: Chile, Ecuador, Ethiopia (Box 32, Folder 355)
    - Printed Material: Germany, Greece-Yugoslavia (Box 32, Folder 356)
    - Printed Material: India, Japan (Box 32, Folder 357)
    - Printed Material: Latin America: Guatemala, Mexico (Box 32, Folder 358)
    - Printed Material: Liberia (Box 32, Folder 358)
    - Printed Material: Lisle Fellowship (Box 32, Folder 359)
    - Printed Material: Overseas (General) (Box 32, Folder 360)
    - Printed Material: Peru (Box 32, Folder 361)
    - Printed Material: South America, Switzerland (Box 32, Folder 362)
    - Printed Material: Turkey (Box 32, Folder 363)
    - USA-USSR Student Exchange: Communications, Notes, Rosters, 1962-1966 (Box 32, Folder 364)
    - USA-USSR Student Exchange: Communications, Notes, Rosters, 1962-1966 (Box 32, Folder 364)
    - USA-USSR Student Exchange: Printed Material, 1959-1961 (Box 32, Folder 366)
    - Miscellaneous Printed Material: Serials, 1960-1963 (Box 32, Folder 367)
- Special Subjects, Series VI
  - Conducting a Meeting, 1948-1950 (Box 33, Folder 368)
  - Christian Purpose and Paris Basis Study: Communications, 1972 (Box 33, Folder 369)
  - Christian Purpose and Paris Basis Study: Reports/Policy Records, 1958, 1969, n.d. (Box 33, Folder 369)
  - Christian Purpose and Paris Basis Study: Printed Materials, 1957-1973, n.d. (Box 33, Folder 370)
  - Lay Movement, 1940-1958, n.d. (Box 33, Folder 371)
  - Membership, 1949, 1955, n.d. (Box 33, Folder 372)
  - National Student Caucus: Communications, 1968, 1970 (Box 33, Folder 373)